<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mrldupuis.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mrldupuis.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-14T22:51:34+00:00</updated><id>https://mrldupuis.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>My personal website. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Raspberry Shake Verification</title><link href="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2024/raspberry_shake_verification/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raspberry Shake Verification"/><published>2024-10-18T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-18T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2024/raspberry_shake_verification</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2024/raspberry_shake_verification/"><![CDATA[<p>In this experiment, I was curious to see how the <a href="https://shop.raspberryshake.org/product/turnkey-iot-home-earth-monitor-rs-3d/">Raspberry Shake 3D</a> would perform compared to the high-quality <a href="https://www.sensequake.com/larze">Sensequake Larze</a> instruments. The Raspberry Shake is a much more affordable option for vibration monitoring, but I wanted to verify its accuracy and see if it could hold up in real-world conditions. To do this, I set it up in my office, where I could take my best shot at make synchronized recordings while controlling the excitation, which consisted of series of progressively larger amplitude taps of my foot on the floor of my office.</p> <p>I ran two 5-minute long tests comparing the Raspberry Shake, which can only record at 100Hz, with the Sensequake Larze recording at 100 Hz and then 1200 Hz.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241018_160813719.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241018_160813719.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241018_160843131.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241018_160843131.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Raspberry shake (left) and Sensequake Larze (right). </div> <p>By comparing the data collected with the trusted Sensequake Larze device, I hoped to get a clearer picture of the Raspberry Shakes’ capabilities and limitations.</p> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/rs_verification/out_unprocessed/TS-1-Raspberry%20Shake.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 0px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> As-recorded velocity time series from the Raspberry Shake (with instrument response removed). </div> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/rs_verification/out/TS-1-Raspberry%20Shake.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 0px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Processed velocity time series from the Raspberry Shake (Tukey windowed, high-pass filtered with 4th order Butterworth filter at 2 Hz, and linearly detrended). </div> <p>One thing that stood out early in the raw data was the large low-frequency drift, especially before any frequency filtering was applied. The raw time series, shown in the first figure, clearly needed some serious processing. To clean up the data, I used a high-pass Butterworth filter to get rid of the low-frequency drift.</p> <p>Next, I wanted to compare the Raspberry Shake’s performance to the Sensequake Larze. Both instruments were set to record at 100 Hz, and when I compared the vertical velocity time series, there were some notable differences in amplitudes. The Fast Fourier Transform (FFT) comparison, shown in the next figure, indicates that the overall spectral shapes between the two instruments were pretty similar.</p> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/rs_verification/out/TS-1-Vertical.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Comparison of the Raspberry Shake and Sensequake Larze vertical velocity time series sampled at 100 Hz. </div> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/rs_verification/out/FFT-1-Vertical.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Fast fourier spectra comparison of the Raspberry Shake and Sensequake Larze vertical velocity time series sampled at 100 Hz. </div> <p>The Raspberry Shake did a decent job. The time series data, while not perfect, were reasonably accurate. However, there were clear issues, particularly with time synchronization between the different channels of the Raspberry Shake. This was evident from the transient wave trains arriving at slightly different times in each direction, which clearly shouldn’t happen. To better illustrate the timing precision of the Raspberry Shake, a second 5-minute long test was completed with the Sensequake Larze instrument recording at 1200 Hz, as shown in the figures below.</p> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/rs_verification/out/TS-2-Hor.%201.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Velocity time series for horizontal component 1 of the Raspberry Shake (100Hz) and the Sensequake Larze, recording at a high sampling rate of 1200 Hz. </div> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/rs_verification/out/TS-2-Hor.%202.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Velocity time series for horizontal component 2 of the Raspberry Shake (100Hz) and the Sensequake Larze, recording at a high sampling rate of 1200 Hz. </div> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/rs_verification/out/TS-2-Vertical.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Velocity time series for the vertical component of the Raspberry Shake (100Hz) and the Sensequake Larze, recording at a high sampling rate of 1200 Hz. </div> <p>Despite these problems, the Raspberry Shake’s FFT results were similar enough to the Larze to suggest that it could be useful for less demanding applications. It’s not quite ready to replace higher-end instruments like the Larze, but for its price, it still has potential.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="signal-processing"/><category term="vibrations"/><category term="RS3D"/><category term="ERT"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In-Office Verification Testing of a Raspberry Shake]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sensequake Larze Instruments</title><link href="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2024/sensequake_larze/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sensequake Larze Instruments"/><published>2024-01-14T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-14T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2024/sensequake_larze</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2024/sensequake_larze/"><![CDATA[<p>VERY excited to start doing some in-office testing with these instruments which <a href="https://geosyntec.com/">Geosyntec</a> has purchased from the nice folks at <a href="https://www.sensequake.com/">Sensequake</a> in Montreal, Canada.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/PXL_20240304_191605795.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/PXL_20240304_191605795.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The new arrivals! </div> <p>With their high precision and low levels of self-noise, these will be excellent instruments for ambient vibration testing of dams.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="signal-processing"/><category term="vibrations"/><category term="dams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The instruments have arrived!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Glenmore Dam Vibration Analysis</title><link href="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2023/glenmore_dam_analysis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glenmore Dam Vibration Analysis"/><published>2023-08-25T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-25T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2023/glenmore_dam_analysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2023/glenmore_dam_analysis/"><![CDATA[<p>Data acquisition was conducted at two locations: (i) free field approximately 100 m downstream of the overflow spillway, i.e., “Free Field”; and (ii) from a public pathway above the dam crest approximately midway along the length of the overflow spillway, i.e., “Dam Crest”.</p> <p>The RS-3D instrument records data in counts, which was converted to units of m/s while also <a href="https://github.com/mrdeqsim/remove_instrument_response">removing instrument response</a>. I also linearly detrended the velocity data and applied a Tukey window in the time domain.</p> <p>The RS 3D time series data exhibits significant low-frequency drift, both at the free field location and at the dam crest. For the dam crest, which was expected to exhibit vibrations due to release of water through the low-level outlet, the amplitudes of vibrations are relatively large, particularly in the instream and vertical directions. Furthermore, and more concerning, transient wave trains at the free field location appear to have different arrival times in each of the three directions, which indicates possible issues with the time synchronization between the channels of the single instrument.</p> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/glenmoredam_20230825/TS-Free%20Field.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 0px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Example segment of velocity time series at the free field location. </div> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/glenmoredam_20230825/TS-Dam%20Crest.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 0px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Example segment of velocity time series at the dam crest. </div> <p>MEM-based power spectral density estimates were also examined for recordings at both the free field location and the dam crest. Spectral peaks apparent in certain directions of the dam crest response support the presence of multiple resonant frequencies. Attributing these resonances to specific component behavior is complicated by the multiple components which contribute to the response at this location, including the dam body, piers, and elevated arch bridge superstructure.</p> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/glenmoredam_20230825/MEM-Free%20Field.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Power spectral density estimates computed via the maximum entropy method at the free field location. </div> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/html/glenmoredam_20230825/MEM-Dam%20Crest.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> Power spectral density estimates computed via the maximum entropy method at the dam crest. </div> <p>So far, based on my testing with the shake, its suitability for ambient vibration testing appears to be limited by its poor time control/synchronization, reliance on external power supply and dedicated laptop, and relatively low sampling rate of only 100 Hz (Nyquist frequency of only 50 Hz). I can’t imagine trying to sync up multiple devices for sampling at multiple locations. However, it may still be a good option for certain applications due to its relatively low cost.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="signal-processing"/><category term="vibrations"/><category term="RS3D"/><category term="dams"/><category term="ERT"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Analyzed the Raspberry Shake data from Glenmore Dam]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Glenmore Dam Testing</title><link href="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2023/glenmore_dam_testing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glenmore Dam Testing"/><published>2023-07-12T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-12T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2023/glenmore_dam_testing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2023/glenmore_dam_testing/"><![CDATA[<p>I went out at the crack of dawn during a long summer day hoping to avoid looking suspicious while there were too many people around.</p> <p>I deployed the velocitmeter for approximately twenty minutes of data acquisition at two locations: (i) a public pathway above dam crest and (ii) at a free field approximately 100 m downstream of the dam. Data was collected on all three instrument channels for a duration of 20 minutes at each location during ambient operating conditions with approximately 1.5 cms of release through the low-level outlet (there is no power generation at Glenmore Dam). It was observed that the reservoir was at full pool and no irregular activities or events were noted which would have perturbed the ambient data collected at either location.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/PXL_20230825_140821473.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/PXL_20230825_140821473.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> View from downstream of the gated overflow spillway, piers, and supported walkway of the Glenmore Dam. </div> <p>At each location, data collection with the RS velocimeter followed the following procedure:</p> <ol> <li>The portable power supply was turned on and connected to the field laptop which was also powered on.</li> <li>The RS-3D was connected to the laptop via ethernet cable.</li> <li>The RS-3D GPS antenna was connected to the RS-3D.</li> <li>The RS-3D was leveled using three leveling pins and a built-in bubble level and recording channels were oriented to be orthogonal to the axis of the dam (crossvalley; instream; and vertical)</li> <li>All wires were cleared from the perimeter of the device and a perimeter was delineated around the device.</li> <li>The RS-3D was plugged into the portable power supply.</li> <li>Data was collected during ambient operating conditions on all three recording channels.</li> </ol> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/PXL_20230825_134425813.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/PXL_20230825_134425813.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/PXL_20230825_140818187.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/PXL_20230825_140818187.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Experimental setup of the Raspberry Shake 3D, portable power supply, laptop, and GPS antenna at Glenmore Dam: above the dam crest (left) and downstream free field (right). </div> <p>I hope to analyze this data to see if I can pick up any machinery harmonics (although there is no power generation at Glenmore Dam) or structural resonances of the gravity monolith or piers.</p> <p>Mostly I’m just glad nobody called the police on me…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="instrumentation"/><category term="vibrations"/><category term="RS3D"/><category term="dams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recorded vibration data from a large dam with the Raspberry Shake]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raspberry Shake Field Kit</title><link href="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2023/raspberry_shake_kit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raspberry Shake Field Kit"/><published>2023-05-15T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-15T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2023/raspberry_shake_kit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mrldupuis.github.io/articles/2023/raspberry_shake_kit/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve assembled a mobile testing kit using a <a href="https://shop.raspberryshake.org/product/turnkey-iot-home-earth-monitor-rs-3d/">Raspberry Shake 3D</a> (RS 3D) velocimeter that I plan to use in the field. I hope to collect some interesting time series data with this to analyze.</p> <p>For the weatherproof case, I decided on a Pelican 1520 Camera Case With Foam (Yellow). I wouldn’t go any smaller than this (its quite tight in there), unfortunately the cost for larger cases increases sharply.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211352540.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211352540.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The complete contents of the mobile testing kit I've assembled. The foam is compressible so the laptop (left) is able to fit in the kit is as well. </div> <p>A dedicated laptop was required to connect to the RS 3D for controlling the device. Make sure to get a laptop with ethernet and USB ports so that you can connect to the shake and also transfer data files to other devices without an internet connection. I was able to get a used laptop from amazon for about $85 USD.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211537340.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211537340.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_212022602.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_212022602.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Small mboile laptop and ethernet cable for sending signals to the RS 3D to initiate and conclude data acquisition. </div> <p>A portable power supply was also required to power both the laptop and RS 3D in the field. I was able to get one from amazon for about $100 USD.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211504951.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211504951.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_212009370.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_212009370.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Small portable power supply with cords to power both the laptop and RS 3D. </div> <p>An optional GPS antenna can also be purchased to provide improved timing in the field. I don’t recommend purchasing one of these, I have had issues with it and I have never been sure whether the RS 3D is using timing based off my laptop or from the GPS antenna. Maybe this is just user error on my part…</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211513851.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211513851.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211517613.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/raspberry_shake/PXL_20241016_211517613.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Zoomed in photos of the RS 3D and antenna. Note that the orientation of the channels (North, East, and Vertical) for the RS 3D are only identified by a small arrow labelled as 'North' on the circuit board. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="instrumentation"/><category term="vibrations"/><category term="RS3D"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I purchased a low cost velocimeter and made a field kit]]></summary></entry></feed>